Clara Beers Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Clara Beers Papers
c. 1865 - 1972
The Clara Beers Papers consist primarily of correspondence and photographs. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
.21 linear feet (1 box)
Beers, Clara Louise Jepson, 1874-1966
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1966.0001
Gift of Emily Martin, 1966-1969.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Clara Louise Jepson Beers was born in New Haven, Connecticut in 1874. She and Clifford Beers, founder of the mental hygiene movement, were married in June 1912. She played an important part in his work, and traveled widely with him, visiting other countries in an effort to form an international organization for improving the care of the mentally ill. Even after her husband's death in 1943, Mrs. Beers continued to be active in mental health organizations, particularly the American Foundation for Mental Hygiene and the World Federation for Mental Health. She died on September 8, 1966.
Beers, Clara Louise Jepson, 1874-1966; Beers, Clifford Whittingham, 1876-1943; National Committee for Mental Hygiene; National Mental Health Association (U.S.)
The Clara Beers Papers consist primarily of correspondence and photographs. Between November 1902 and August 1903 she took an extensive tour of Europe, and many letters to her parents relate her experiences. The strong bond she had with her parents, especially her father, is apparent in these letters. Clara maintained two diaries with brief entries, and there is also other correspondence regarding Clara's father, Benjamin Jepson, a professor of music, and her brothers, Arthur and Harry Jepson. A number of photographs portray Clara, including one in her wedding dress, as well as several of her as a child and a young woman. Other photographs depict her family and Clara and Clifford’s summer home in Belgrade, Maine. Emily Martin’s correspondence about Clara’s health in her last years and obituaries complete the collection. The dates for the collection are 1865-1972. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Passport for Clara Jepson’s European trip, 1902 (Box 1)
  - Bon voyage letters to Clara Jepson from her friends Ed Oriatt and Fanny Oriatt, 1902 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Mr. & Mrs. Benjamin Jepson to their daughter Clara Louise Jepson in Europe, 1902 - 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe written to her family, 1902 - 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe written to her family, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe written to her family, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe written to her family, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe written to her family, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe written to her family, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Clara Jepson while in Europe written to her family, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between Clara Jepson and her father, Benjamin Jepson and letters re Clara's marriage to Clifford Beers and of Benjamin Jepson's death, 1882 - 1914 (Box 1)
  - Diary of Clara Beers, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Diary of Clara Beers, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Account about life of Benjamin Jepson and news clipping, 1913 - 1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with and concerning Clara's brothers, Arthur and Harry Jepson, 1904 - 1954 (Box 1)
  - Obituary of Seth Bingham, former student of Harry Jepson, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Letter and news clipping re first annual Beers lecture, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Four photographs of Clara Jepson and friends taken in Florence, Italy, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Nineteen photographs of Clara Jepson and her family, c. 1865 - 1912 (Box 1)
  - Wedding photograph, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Nine photographs of the Beers’ summer cottage in Belgrade Lakes, Maine, and of their garden in their home in Englewood, New Jersey, 1939; Undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph dedicated to Clara Beers depicting three leaders in the mental health movement, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Clara Beers and others at 50th anniversary dinner of founding of National Committee for Mental Hygiene and program for dinner, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified photograph, Undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Emily Martin re condition of Clara Beers during her last years, 1965 - 1966 (Box 1)
  - Obituary of Clara Beers, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Obituary of Clara Beers in NAMH Reporter, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Biographical sketch of Clara Beers prepared by Emily Martin, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Memos by Emily Martin re collection, 1966 - 1969 (Box 1)